<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Homophony</title>
<link>https://homophony.quest/notes.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://homophony.quest/notes.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Music blog for motivation to play more music</description>
<image>
<url>https://homophony.quest/images/notesE_0.jpg</url>
<title>Homophony</title>
<link>https://homophony.quest/notes.html</link>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.4.533</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Modes…sigh</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/15_1_13_24_modes/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/15_1_13_24_modes/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“musical modes. Ionian, Dorian, Phrygian, Lydian, Mixolydian, Aeolian and Locrian. piano. theory. music. colorful. lino cut. cartoon. illustration. thinking.” - dreamshaper-xl-turbo</p>
</div></div><p>I’m not friends with modes yet. Barely an acquaintance, even after all these years.</p>
<p>Today’s practice is focusing on modes, yet again. This morning I am thinking of modes like a Donald Rumsfeld quote. Modes for me are known knowns, known unknowns, and unknown unknowns.</p>
<section id="modes-as-known-knowns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="modes-as-known-knowns">Modes as known knowns</h2>
<p>I’m not sure when I first learned about modes, but probably some time in middle school. Since then I have– in a definitional sense– known what they were.</p>
<p>The way I encoded them as a piano player was in terms of the C major scale. There are 7 modes of the major scale, corresponding to each key of the major scale. Each mode involves playing the major scale from a different root note. This got turned into a heuristic like, play all the white keys from C to C…then play them from D to D, E to E, and so on. Those are the modes. That’s it. Also, the major scale modes have these Greek names:</p>
<table class="table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Mode Name</th>
<th>Starting Note</th>
<th>Notes in C Major</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Ionian</td>
<td>I</td>
<td>CDEFGABC</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Dorian</td>
<td>II</td>
<td>DEFGACBD</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Phrygian</td>
<td>III</td>
<td>EFGABCDE</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Lydian</td>
<td>IV</td>
<td>FGABCDEF</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Mixolydian</td>
<td>V</td>
<td>GABCDEFG</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Aeolian</td>
<td>VI</td>
<td>ABCDEFGA</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Locrian</td>
<td>VII</td>
<td>BCDEFGAB</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The mode concept is a descriptive one. Other scales have can be described as having modes using the same principles as above.</p>
<p>That’s about as far the known knowns go for me. I don’t really think in terms of modes when I play. Also, that’s why I’m working on thinking in terms of modes again. For the extra flavor and different perspective that they bring.</p>
</section>
<section id="modes-as-known-unknowns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="modes-as-known-unknowns">Modes as known unknowns</h2>
<p>There’s lots of other stuff that I in some sense “know” about modes. But, in practice, that conceptual knowledge is not well integrated into my playing.</p>
<p>The best example is that I never really bothered to automatize the modes across all of the keys. Oops. Here again is a strange failure of generalization.</p>
<p>On the one hand, I have practiced all of the modes across all of the keys. For example, over the past month I’ve been doing a lot of major scale work going up and down the major scale in every key, in every mode. I can play them all reasonably quickly now. So, that’s great. I must know my modes right? Not really.</p>
<p>On the other hand, I wasn’t thinking about modes, mode names, or modal relationships as I was playing through those scales. So, for example, I knew it would be hard to play C scales in the different modes. Of course I know C ionian. But, what is C dorian? Mind goes blank. Then slowly, “yes, C is the II of Bb”, so then C dorian is, “play a Bb major scale starting from C.” Then, what is the third mode even? Can’t remember…oh yes, Phrygian. What is C Phrygian? ummm….blah.</p>
<p>Of course, I can play an Ab major scale, but thinking of C Phygrian as Ab is one of those known unknowns. It’s the kind of missing connections I know are there, but haven’t bothered to glue together.</p>
<p>More generally, I’m hoping that working through modes will help me firm up these kinds of relations between notes so that they are within striking distance of my finger tips. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>C as a I (Ionian) in C</p></li>
<li><p>C as a II (dorian) in Bb</p></li>
<li><p>C as a III (phrygian) in Ab</p></li>
<li><p>C as a IV (Lydian) in G</p></li>
<li><p>C as a V (Mixolydian) in F</p></li>
<li><p>C as a VI (Aeolian) in Eb</p></li>
<li><p>C as a VII (Locrian) in Db</p></li>
</ul>
<p>And, then all of those same relationships for every note.</p>
</section>
<section id="modes-and-unknown-unknowns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="modes-and-unknown-unknowns">Modes and unknown unknowns</h2>
<p>I suppose this is the stuff I’ll discover later on when I know my modes better.</p>
<p>One example from this morning was noticing patterns of harmonic ambiguity that are mildly interesting. For example, let’s say you play a C and G, which could be described as a perfect fifth in the key of C. What else could it be? Those notes are in the C major scale, so they could imply C Ionian. Those notes are also in the Bb major scale (the II and VI), so they could imply Bb as the tonal center, and in that case playing notes from C dorian would help fill in that implication. The same goes for all of the other modes of C (except for locrian where the G is diminished). And this is a fun little toy to play with, like a jack-in-the-box. Playing Cs and Gs is like turning the gear of the box, building expectations about what kind of jack will pop up, and then OMG, it’s a locrian scale.</p>
</section>
<section id="modes-by-accident" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="modes-by-accident">Modes by accident</h2>
<p>I still can’t remember the names of modes. And, I haven’t encoded them in terms of their accidental values. So, that’s why I am making this table. These are the different modes of C.</p>
<table class="table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 17%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 28%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Mode Name</th>
<th>Accidental</th>
<th>Major scale</th>
<th>C scale</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Ionian I</td>
<td>none</td>
<td>C</td>
<td>C D E F G A B C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Dorian II</td>
<td>bIII, bVII</td>
<td>Bb (C is -ii)</td>
<td>C D Eb F G A Bb C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Phrygian III</td>
<td>bII, bIII, bVI, bVII</td>
<td>Ab (C is -iii)</td>
<td>C Db Eb F G Ab Bb C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Lydian IV</td>
<td>#IV</td>
<td>G (C is iv)</td>
<td>C D E F# G A B C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Mixolydian V</td>
<td>bVII</td>
<td>F (C is v)</td>
<td>C D E F G A Bb C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Aeolian VI</td>
<td>bIII, bVI, bVII</td>
<td>Eb (C is -vi)</td>
<td>C D Eb F G Ab Bb C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Locrian VII</td>
<td>bII, bIII, bV, bVI, bVII</td>
<td>Db (C is vii)</td>
<td>C Db Eb F Gb Ab Bb C</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>So, a new goal will be to play the modes in each key from this point of view.</p>
<p>The I (ionian), IV (lydian), and V (mixolydian) modes are “major” flavor, and the II (dorian), III (phrygian), IV (aeolian), and VII (locrian) modes are “minor” flavor.</p>
<p>I’m going to re-order the modes in terms of the circle of fifths.</p>
<table class="table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 17%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 28%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Mode Name</th>
<th>Accidental</th>
<th>Major scale</th>
<th>C scale</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Lydian IV</td>
<td>#IV</td>
<td>G (C is iv)</td>
<td>C D E F# G A B C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Ionian I</td>
<td>none</td>
<td>C</td>
<td>C D E F G A B C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Mixolydian V</td>
<td>bVII</td>
<td>F (C is v)</td>
<td>C D E F G A Bb C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Dorian II</td>
<td>bIII, bVII</td>
<td>Bb (C is -ii)</td>
<td>C D Eb F G A Bb C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Aeolian VI</td>
<td>bIII, bVI, bVII</td>
<td>Eb (C is -vi)</td>
<td>C D Eb F G Ab Bb C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Phrygian III</td>
<td>bII, bIII, bVI, bVII</td>
<td>Ab (C is -iii)</td>
<td>C Db Eb F G Ab Bb C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Locrian VII</td>
<td>bII, bIII, bV, bVI, bVII</td>
<td>Db (C is vii)</td>
<td>C Db Eb F Gb Ab Bb C</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>From this point of view there are five increasingly “minor” modes, going from Mixolydian to Locrian. Thinking in terms of what spices are added to the C major, the mixolydian adds a Bb. If you play a C and the dominant 7th (Bb), then there is a kind of question…how many more minor spices are there going to be? When I’m cooking a minor chord, there’s lots of spices to be added. There’s less major spice options, but throw in the tri-tone once in a while I guess.</p>
<p>More notes…The same table as above, using arabic numerals, and re-ordering in terms how the flats are added in the circle of fifths.</p>
<table class="table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 17%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 28%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Mode Name</th>
<th>Accidental</th>
<th>Major scale</th>
<th>C scale</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Lydian IV</td>
<td>#4</td>
<td>G (C is iv)</td>
<td>C D E F# G A B C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Ionian I</td>
<td>none</td>
<td>C</td>
<td>C D E F G A B C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Mixolydian V</td>
<td>b7</td>
<td>F (C is v)</td>
<td>C D E F G A Bb C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Dorian II</td>
<td>b7, b3</td>
<td>Bb (C is -ii)</td>
<td>C D Eb F G A Bb C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Aeolian VI</td>
<td>b7, b3, b6</td>
<td>Eb (C is -vi)</td>
<td>C D Eb F G Ab Bb C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Phrygian III</td>
<td>b7, b3, b6, b2</td>
<td>Ab (C is -iii)</td>
<td>C Db Eb F G Ab Bb C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Locrian VII</td>
<td>b7, b3, b6, b2, b5</td>
<td>Db (C is vii)</td>
<td>C Db Eb F Gb Ab Bb C</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="modes-as-slashpolychords" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="modes-as-slashpolychords">Modes as slash/polychords</h2>
<p>I’ve seen different definitions of slash and polychords. One definition of a slash chord (say D/F#) is to play the numerator triad (D) with the denominator bass note (F#). And, a polychord would be playing one triad with the right hand (D) and another with the left hand (F#).</p>
<p>Another way to think of playing modes is in terms of slash chords or poly chords; or, I guess slash scales or poly scales. For example, consider a G/C. That could indicate a G major scale over a C bass note. Playing the G major scale starting and ending on C is the same as C lydian.</p>
<p>In the next table the note in the denominator is the root. The note in the numerator is the major scale to be played over the root (starting and ending on the root). The roman numerals show interval relations between the root and scale. For example, in the lydian column, the root is the fourth note in the corresponding scale (C is the fourth of G, G is the fourth of C). Modifying the major scale in the denominator by the accidental yields the major scale in the numerator (For Bb/C, flattening the 37 in C is B-&gt; Bb and E -&gt; Eb, which then turns the C scale into a Bb scale). The table is arranged in terms of the circle of fifths.</p>
<table class="table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 12%">
<col style="width: 12%">
<col style="width: 18%">
<col style="width: 12%">
<col style="width: 14%">
<col style="width: 15%">
<col style="width: 14%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Lydian</th>
<th>Ionian</th>
<th>Mixolydian</th>
<th>Dorian</th>
<th>Aeolian</th>
<th>Phrygian</th>
<th>Locrian</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Majory</td>
<td>Major</td>
<td>Majorish</td>
<td>Minor</td>
<td>even</td>
<td>more</td>
<td>MINOR</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>IV</td>
<td>I</td>
<td>V</td>
<td>II</td>
<td>VI</td>
<td>III</td>
<td>VII</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>#4</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>b7</td>
<td>b73</td>
<td>b736</td>
<td>b7362</td>
<td>b73625</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>G/C</td>
<td>C/C</td>
<td>F/C</td>
<td>Bb/C</td>
<td>Eb/C</td>
<td>Ab/C</td>
<td>Db/C</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>C/F</td>
<td>F/F</td>
<td>Bb/F</td>
<td>Eb/F</td>
<td>Ab/F</td>
<td>Db/F</td>
<td>Gb/F</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>F/Bb</td>
<td>Bb/Bb</td>
<td>Eb/Bb</td>
<td>Ab/Bb</td>
<td>Db/Bb</td>
<td>Gb/Bb</td>
<td>B/Bb</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Bb/Eb</td>
<td>Eb/Eb</td>
<td>Ab/Eb</td>
<td>Db/Eb</td>
<td>Gb/Eb</td>
<td>B/Eb</td>
<td>E/Eb</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Eb/Ab</td>
<td>Ab/Ab</td>
<td>Db/Ab</td>
<td>Gb/Ab</td>
<td>B/Ab</td>
<td>E/Ab</td>
<td>A/Ab</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Ab/Db</td>
<td>Db/Db</td>
<td>Gb/Db</td>
<td>B/Db</td>
<td>E/Db</td>
<td>A/Db</td>
<td>D/Db</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Db/Gb</td>
<td>Gb/Gb</td>
<td>B/Gb</td>
<td>E/Gb</td>
<td>A/Gb</td>
<td>D/Gb</td>
<td>G/Gb</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Gb/B</td>
<td>B/B</td>
<td>E/B</td>
<td>A/B</td>
<td>D/B</td>
<td>G/B</td>
<td>C/B</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>B/E</td>
<td>E/E</td>
<td>A/E</td>
<td>D/E</td>
<td>G/E</td>
<td>C/E</td>
<td>F/E</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>E/A</td>
<td>A/A</td>
<td>D/A</td>
<td>G/A</td>
<td>C/A</td>
<td>F/A</td>
<td>Bb/A</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>A/D</td>
<td>D/D</td>
<td>G/D</td>
<td>C/D</td>
<td>F/D</td>
<td>Bb/D</td>
<td>Eb/D</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>D/G</td>
<td>G/G</td>
<td>C/G</td>
<td>F/G</td>
<td>Bb/G</td>
<td>Eb/G</td>
<td>Ab/G</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Thinking in terms of the circle of fifths. Playing a slash scale one fifth above the root is Lydian. Playing a scale in the root is Ionian. Playing slash scales down the circle of fifths (anti-clockwise) is Mixolydian, Dorian, Aeolian, Phrygian, Locrian.</p>
</section>
<section id="playing-the-sound-of-the-modes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="playing-the-sound-of-the-modes">Playing the sound of the modes</h2>
<p>Note to self to just get into it.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>modes</category>
  <category>scales</category>
  <category>music theory</category>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/15_1_13_24_modes/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/15_1_13_24_modes/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The VERY Expressive Osmose</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/14_1_12_24_osmose/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/14_1_12_24_osmose/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“synthesizer dreamland. explosions of joyful expression. expressive happiness. dancing music. colorful. neon. modular synth. eurorack. cartoon, woodcut, linocut.” - dreamshaper-xl-turbo</p>
</div></div><p>I’ve been really curious about the <a href="https://www.expressivee.com/2-osmose">Expressive Osmose</a> keyboard for a while now. So, I picked one up yesterday.</p>
<p>Basically all I have to say is: HOLY WOW.</p>
<p>I might have more to say later, and I may add notes to this post about the osmose as I go through the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Y02SCLQSnzw">7 stages of osmose ownership</a>.</p>
<p>For, now I need to get back to pitch bending every note into a tornado of meowing cats.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Actually, this was the expressive controller/synthesizer I was looking for – reply to Obi-Wan Kenobi</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Early afternoon update. I have been noodling away roughly alphabetically through the 500 presets. I’m just starting the ones that begin with C. It’s easy to get lost in fun for hours doing this. Not that I want to take the fun away, but I should start integrating this a little bit more into my setup. Probably the next step will be recording the noodles.</p>
<p>Here are some notes so far on playing the osmose. These are notes to self to help me progress through this thing.</p>
<section id="velocity-and-pressure" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="velocity-and-pressure">Velocity and pressure</h2>
<p>The osmose has several dimensions of expressive control. Like most standard midi keyboards it has note velocity, but it also has pressure, aftertouch, and pitch bend for each key independently, with 24 voice polyphony!</p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://product.hstatic.net/1000342432/product/1-roland-hp-5600.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>A digression into my past life of utterly not liking midi keyboards. I grew up playing a Roland 5600 with a MC-300 (or 500?) and MT-32 (where much was had with the orchestra hit sound). I would go to my piano teacher’s houses for lessons on a real piano, and practice on the midi piano at home. It was fun to make different sounds on the roland, but I always wanted a real piano as a kid.</p>
<p>I still love the action of a real piano. It turns out I also love the action of my rhodes 88 key electric piano. But, I have never loved the action of any midi keyboard that I have ever owned or played. Not the hammer action ones. Not any of them.</p>
<p>In 2019 I got to play a CS-80 one time in Melbourne and I could not believe how much a difference polyphonic aftertouch made. It’s so sad that midi keyboards suck so much for so long.</p>
<p>Maybe I didn’t spend enough time with the other midi keyboards that I didn’t like. Most recently I brought home a Nord 88 key stage piano to use a controller, and it was just ok…one key broke, and there is an uncurable noisy power supply. Plus, these things never feel like an instrument to me, so they just constantly suck joy.</p>
<p>I have tried to adjust velocity curves and find something that seems better, but never got there. It’s possible I just don’t like how velocity is usually implemented, or that velocity is missing something for me. In any case, when I play on my acoustic or electric piano, even though both keyboards have very different action, they are both very playable and immediately expressive. I don’t have think about it, the expression is just there.</p>
<p>This is what I now adore about the osmose. The expression is right there at my finger tips.</p>
<p>I really like that they have pressure per key too.</p>
</section>
<section id="squishy-goodness" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="squishy-goodness">Squishy goodness</h2>
<p>It’s hard to describe what the action feels like. There is some initial resistance to the keys, but not too much. This is great for light and/or bouncy tapping and slowly applying pressure to the keys. Many of the presets make sound from pressure alone, and sometimes different sounds from pressure or velocity.</p>
<p>The aftertouch is the best feeling aftertouch I’ve ever played. There is a slight difference in resistance when you get to aftertouch land, and way more travel down into the aftertouch than on typical midi keyboards. It feels like the key keeps going down into it’s aftertouch home, where it belongs sometimes.</p>
<p>Similarly, the key’s pick up side-to-side wiggling throughout the travel of the key and into aftertouch range. This parameter is usually applied to pitch bend. It get’s a bit easier to wiggle when the key is pressed down a bit, but over all it’s very natural.</p>
</section>
<section id="presets" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="presets">Presets</h2>
<p>Lots of juicy stuff in the presets, all powered by <a href="https://www.hakenaudio.com/sound-engine">EaganMatrix</a>. It’ll be a while before I go into that thing.</p>
<p>There are a few onboard effects like a reverb and delays. The reverb can sound pretty good, especially with extend “on”.</p>
<p>I don’t like menu diving, and it’s pretty fast to make changes to sounds and to sensitivity parameters of the controller. Very happy with that.</p>
<p>Need to go play it some more.</p>
</section>
<section id="mpe-controller" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mpe-controller">MPE controller</h2>
<p>I’ve got it hooked up to the OB-6 and it works very well. Whenever I need the sound to go to 11, I just back it up with some OB-6. The more the scarier.</p>
</section>
<section id="recording-midi-in-ableton-live" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recording-midi-in-ableton-live">Recording midi in ableton live</h2>
<p>I was recording for a bit with one midi track and one audio track. Things seemed to be going fine, but Ableton started freezing up once in a while, and the midi recordings were sometimes really off. The likely culprit is me trying to record MPE midi for the first time.</p>
<p>It seems there are some MPE midi settings that are important, like from this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Xxtjvn5PrUo">video</a></p>
<p>Still crashing ableton a bunch. A problem for another day.</p>
<!--

Velocity and pressure

- i'm a piano player and love the action of some pianos...
- not liking most/if any midi keyboards that I've used in the past.
- is this to do with how velocity is implemented?

Loving the pressure sensitivity along with velocity implementation.

Really fun icons for the macros and other controls

Fairly quick to access aspects of sound control...sensitivity adjustments are great, feels like I'm tweaking an instrument.
- a little awkward getting around...matrix


-->


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>gear</category>
  <category>osmose</category>
  <category>MPE</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/14_1_12_24_osmose/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/14_1_12_24_osmose/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Turtle TRS-80 variations</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/13_1_9_24_turtle_ep133/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/13_1_9_24_turtle_ep133/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“Can’t remember exactly. TRS computers, turtle connecting to the universe with a modem. Thundercats. woodcut cartoon vibes.” - dreamshaper-xl-turbo</p>
</div></div><div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/oEqS-yKuJQ8?si=vsCeNk1WKdqAGTIQ" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>I did my piano practice in A major today following the 7th chord themes from previous posts.</p>
<p>Then I accidentally spent too much time generating turtle cartoons with dreamshaper. So, I made a beat with the EP-133 and set them to music.</p>
<p>So many variations of the same thing.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>track</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/13_1_9_24_turtle_ep133/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/13_1_9_24_turtle_ep133/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>D major practice</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/12_1_8_24_Dmajor/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/12_1_8_24_Dmajor/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“D major scale. Piano. Circle of fifths. D major 7th chords played on an infinite universe piano. synthesizer keyboard universe.” - dreamshaper-xl-turbo</p>
</div></div><p>Continuing from yesterday’s G major practice I moved onto D major.</p>
<p>Played the D major scale up and down using 7th chords. Did this multiple times with each inversion.</p>
<p>Noted that I liked the sound of the 3rd inversion the best. Ran up and down enough times that I could play fairly fluently, almost into melody territory. Will likely continue this sort of practice across other keys.</p>
<hr>
<p>Aside…I’ve been messing around with huggingface models as a possible way to generate visual stimuli for some experiments this semester. The class of latent consistency models can generate decent images fairly quickly. This morning I downloaded the “dreamshaper-xl-turbo” model to test it out. Today’s blog picture was generated from this model.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/12_1_8_24_Dmajor/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/12_1_8_24_Dmajor/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Screaming modems</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/12_1_8_24_screaming_modems/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/12_1_8_24_screaming_modems/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“massive synthesizer, dueling guitar playing giant robots. guitar looks like an old fashioned modem. speakers. stereo. modular synth. eurorack. cartoon, thundercats, woodcut, linocut.” - dreamshaper-xl-turbo</p>
</div></div><p><audio controls=""> <source src="screaming_modems.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<p>Sometimes I’ll just give up and go with screaming modems dueling in stereo sonic nonsense…that is unnecessarily too long…courtesy of the OB-6. Not much else to say really.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>track</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/12_1_8_24_screaming_modems/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/12_1_8_24_screaming_modems/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Back in the saddle</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/11_1_7_24_saddle/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/11_1_7_24_saddle/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“a piano riding a horse. piano rides horse. piano riding a horse. piano keys. synthesizer keyboard.” - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p>Vacation was nice. Easing back into practice.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Played through each scale using 7ths chords going anti-clockwise through the circle of fifths.</li>
</ol>
<p>I’ve overplayed the C major scale for decades and should probably just stop practicing in C. At the same time, I can rip through the C major scale using 7th chords very quickly. In addition to practice, it seems easier to “see” the 7th chords in C major– they all have the same shape and use only white keys. It would be nice to have that immediacy for all of the other scales, and this is something I’m slowly working towards.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Did a little bit of focused practice in G. Played through the G Major scale using 7th chords to build up speed. Played up and down using each inversion of each 7th chord.</li>
</ol>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/11_1_7_24_saddle/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/11_1_7_24_saddle/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Quantum Freeloader</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/10_12_30_23_Quantum_Freeloader/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/10_12_30_23_Quantum_Freeloader/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>Tape cassette robot shooting lasers of music at a concert with massive speakers and a universe in the sky. - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p><audio controls=""> <source src="Quantum_freeloader_take_1_01.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<p>This is a mash-up of a few things I’ve been working on and covered in previous posts.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>I spent some time learning solo parts from Wynton Kelly’s piano solo on Miles Davis’ Freddie Freeloader</p></li>
<li><p>I did some beat recreation from Quantic’s Life in the Rain. This ended up as a midi track with lots of added notes and modified note probabilities to make the beat have more natural and interesting variation.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>The track is in the style of Freddie Freeloader. The chords and melody are different, but they are still variations of the general idea.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/10_12_30_23_Quantum_Freeloader/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/10_12_30_23_Quantum_Freeloader/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Breaking out of the 4 bar drum loop</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/9_12_29_23_morethan4/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/9_12_29_23_morethan4/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>A tape cassette robot playing a drum kit. Massive speakers in the background. Super funky beats - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p>I have a really lazy habit with drum beats that I need to fix. It goes something like this: make a 4 bar beat, loop it, jam endlessly inside a 4 bar beat that gets boring and has no fills.</p>
<p>Yesterday I had some fun recreating a 4 bar beat from Quantic’s “Life in the Rain”. Today, the plan is to make this into a 12-bar beat with a reasonable amount of variation and some simple fills.</p>
<p>…Does some things in Ableton that didn’t take that long…Should do this kind of thing more often. Now I have a 12-bar drum part with a decent amount of variation. But, it’s on my upstairs computer and I need to get this into a new project on my downstairs computer. I’ve been using Ableton since forever and I don’t think I’ve ever tried to copy or import a midi track from one project to another. It must be possible. Going to play some music over these drums.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/9_12_29_23_morethan4/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/9_12_29_23_morethan4/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Recreating a beat from Quantic’s Life in the Rain</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/8_12_27_23_quantic_rain/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/8_12_27_23_quantic_rain/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>Album cover - The 5th Exotic by Quantic</p>
</div></div><ol type="1">
<li>Record this thing into Ableton and grab the beat.</li>
</ol>
<p>Sidenote. Attempting this on a new mac. I was going to record from Apple Music into Ableton, but I wasn’t setup for that. I used to use soundflower to route audio, and now I’m going to try <a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/loopback/">loopback</a>.</p>
<p>Really annoying to install on my new mac because of the process of allowing kernel extensions. ugh. Will it work? OK, it worked.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Here’s 8 bars from Quantic. The first 4 are a bit of cymabals, and the beat comes in on the last 4. It’s the last 4 that I’m interested.</li>
</ol>
<p><audio controls=""> <source src="main_beat.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Set up some drums in Ableton and MIDIfy this beat.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>This took a little while. Not a huge fan of penciling in midi markers on my computer to make beats.</li>
<li>Set up a basic drum rack, found some close enough sounds</li>
<li>Used the EP-133 as a midi controller to pound in the beats, that was more fun</li>
<li>Nudged things around etc.</li>
<li>got close</li>
</ul>
<p>I ended up with this version of the main beat:</p>
<p><audio controls=""> <source src="midi_100.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<p>Then, what’s fun with having everything as a midi note is to play around with note probability, and with adding hits that weren’t there, but now have a small probability of being there. Here’s an example of setting most of the sounds to a 50% probability.</p>
<p><audio controls=""> <source src="midi_50.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<p>It’s more airy, but still carries the groove.</p>
<p>Practice notes: More or less accomplished the goal for this drum recreation exercise. Did not mix the drum voices to taste.</p>
<p>To Do:</p>
<ul>
<li>[] Use this somehow.</li>
<li>[] Learn a little bit more about saving midi clips/audio etc. in ableton so that it is easy for me to re-use this later.</li>
<li>[] See about programming this beat into the Varigate 8+, and or Hermod, so I have a modular version</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/8_12_27_23_quantic_rain/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/8_12_27_23_quantic_rain/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Blogging for music motivation</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/1_12_27_23_blog/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I had some time at the end of my semester to play piano more than usual. This semester that meant I actually played the piano, instead of not playing the piano.</p>
<p>Clearly I need to make time for more piano. I’m hoping this blog will keep me somewhat organized and motivated to stay on target.</p>
<p>The blog is built with <a href="https://quarto.org">quarto</a>, and this post is just changing the structure a little bit so that each post is it’s own post, rather than a bunch of posts on a single page.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>quarto</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/1_12_27_23_blog/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/1_12_27_23_blog/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Freddie Freeloader Wynton Kelly solo</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/7_12_27_23_freddie/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/7_12_27_23_freddie/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“A small penguin wearing headphones. The penguin listens to the music from the headphones. The penguin sits in front of a piano. The penguin can imagine the musical notes in a tornado above her head.” - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p>I spent most of yesterday working through Wynton Kelly’s solo on Freddie Freeloader (from Miles Davis’s Kind of Blue). My plan for this post is to talk a little bit about what I did, and what I learned.</p>
<p>A slight detour though. It’s been very nice to have some clear time to actually practice piano, let alone enough time to break down a solo. When I was a kid the advice was to listen to recordings and learn to play from them by ear. In some cases I was able to do this (with difficulty, because I didn’t spend enough time practicing this way), but for the most part I didn’t have the recordings to listen to. Flash-forward to today and almost everything is available to stream. That’s amazing when you’re trying to learn something by ear. Not only that, but the internet is full of musicians sharing their practice tips. It’s almost overwhelming, but in a good way.</p>
<p>For Freddie Freeloader I checked out a couple of YouTube videos before trying the solo myself: a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XSjWOTbL5ew">transcription video</a> and an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZxfawXcpuaQ">analysis video</a>. Then I played the song a couple times before heading downstairs. Here’s the breakdown process I used this time.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Play the original recording into a track on Ableton live</li>
<li>Cut the track so that it starts properly on the first bar</li>
<li>Turn off “warp”, and then adjust the tempo of Ableton until the beats in the track line up properly with the bars in Ableton.</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/7_12_27_23_freddie/Screenshot 2023-12-27 at 7.56.08 AM.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The purple track is the original recording. The selected area is the first two bars, and it is possible to loop the selection and/or slow it down without changing the pitch (by turning warp back on).</p>
<p>I wasn’t particularly interested in learning the solo to play it note for note straight through. But, I was interested in trying out each little part and thinking about how the notes were used as phrases.</p>
<p>So, I worked in sections of two bars, looped each section, then played over top on the Fender Rhodes until I thought I had the line. The blue track are my 2 bar recordings on the Rhodes.</p>
<p>I didn’t have time to get through the whole solo, just the first 12 bars, and it got a little messy at the end. Oh well. Had lots of fun.</p>
<p><audio controls=""> <source src="Freddie_solo.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<p>Practice notes: I ended up practicing the first phrase through the circle of fifths this morning.</p>
<p><audio controls=""> <source src="freddie_phrase.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/7_12_27_23_freddie/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/7_12_27_23_freddie/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rootless 9th chords</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/6_12_26_23_rootless9th/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/6_12_26_23_rootless9th/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“An underground lair of piano playing rabbits. Above the rabbits are the roots of carrots that have been eaten by rabbits as they play piano.” - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p>Today’s exercise was running I∆7add9 chords through the circle of fifths.</p>
<p>The first row shows the notes of the C major scale with corresponding numbers. The 9th note is the same as the second note in the scale.</p>
<p>The second row shows the concept of constructing chords from thirds. From this perspective, you get all of the notes in the scale going up by thirds, but the 9th, 11th, and 13th note are out of their normal order.</p>
<p>This exercise focuses on the “rootless” 9th chord on the bottom row. That one has a major 3rd, a perfect fifth, a major 7th, and a 9th.</p>
<table class="table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 6%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>1</th>
<th>2</th>
<th>3</th>
<th>4</th>
<th>5</th>
<th>6</th>
<th>7</th>
<th>8</th>
<th>9</th>
<th>10</th>
<th>11</th>
<th>12</th>
<th>13</th>
<th>14</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>C</strong></td>
<td>D</td>
<td><strong>E</strong></td>
<td>F</td>
<td><strong>G</strong></td>
<td>A</td>
<td><strong>B</strong></td>
<td>C</td>
<td><strong>D</strong></td>
<td>E</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>G</td>
<td>A</td>
<td>B</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>C</td>
<td></td>
<td>E</td>
<td></td>
<td>G</td>
<td></td>
<td>B</td>
<td></td>
<td>D</td>
<td></td>
<td>F</td>
<td></td>
<td>A</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>E</td>
<td></td>
<td>G</td>
<td></td>
<td>B</td>
<td></td>
<td>D</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>In the exercise I played these chords clockwise and anti-clockwise through the circle of fifths. I usually used my left hand for the bass note and to remind myself where I was in the circle. Then I played versions of the 9th chord. They all have a smashing pumpkins kind of vibe.</p>
<p>One reason I chose this exercise is to press harder on deprogramming my root conditioning. These chords don’t have the root in them, so they must be good for that (e.g., thinking about doing something in C, but not playing C, or only playing around C).</p>
<p>Another musical connection is that these 9th chords are the same as a III-7 chord. So, an E minor 7th is a C major 7th add 9.</p>
<p>Cognitive science connections: As a sidenote, my day job is a cognitive psychology professor who studies skill-learning. I’ve been meaning to do some piano skill research and I even have the keyboards in my lab to do it. So, as I go through these exercises it’s been fun thinking about issues like how does training on some musical ideas transfer to others.</p>
<p>For example, I’m already fairly fluid at playing the circle of fifths in different ways. If I’m playing single notes, I can go through the circle very quickly. It’s slower for chords, but still fairly quick. I’ve been practicing my 7th chords through the circle, so I can already go through the circle playing minor 7th chords fairly quickly. However, it turns out I can not do these 9th chords quickly. There should be pretty good transfer here because the 9th chords are exactly the same as the minor 7th chords that I have already practiced.</p>
<p>In terms of minor 7th chords I had been practicing these chords, with the root in the bass.</p>
<table class="table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>1</th>
<th>2</th>
<th>3</th>
<th>4</th>
<th>5</th>
<th>6</th>
<th>7</th>
<th>8</th>
<th>9</th>
<th>10</th>
<th>11</th>
<th>12</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>E-7</td>
<td>B-7</td>
<td>Gb-7</td>
<td>Db-7</td>
<td>Ab-7</td>
<td>Eb-7</td>
<td>Bb-7</td>
<td>F-7</td>
<td>C-7</td>
<td>G-7</td>
<td>D-7</td>
<td>A-7</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>E</td>
<td>B</td>
<td>Gb</td>
<td>Db</td>
<td>Ab</td>
<td>Eb</td>
<td>Bb</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>C</td>
<td>G</td>
<td>D</td>
<td>A</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>But, I had not been practicing those chords with the following bass notes.</p>
<table class="table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>1</th>
<th>2</th>
<th>3</th>
<th>4</th>
<th>5</th>
<th>6</th>
<th>7</th>
<th>8</th>
<th>9</th>
<th>10</th>
<th>11</th>
<th>12</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>E-7</td>
<td>B-7</td>
<td>Gb-7</td>
<td>Db-7</td>
<td>Ab-7</td>
<td>Eb-7</td>
<td>Bb-7</td>
<td>F-7</td>
<td>C-7</td>
<td>G-7</td>
<td>D-7</td>
<td>A-7</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>C</td>
<td>G</td>
<td>D</td>
<td>A</td>
<td>E</td>
<td>B</td>
<td>Gb</td>
<td>Db</td>
<td>Ab</td>
<td>Eb</td>
<td>Bb</td>
<td>F</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Generalization is so fickle sometimes.</p>
<p>Also, I have some super-biased thirds. What’s the third of C -&gt; E. No problem, that’s fast. A -&gt; C, G -&gt; B. But, B ———&gt; Eb. That one hurts. Eb seems too far away to be a third. In any case. I need to flatten out this distribution at some point.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/6_12_26_23_rootless9th/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/6_12_26_23_rootless9th/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>7th first II-V-I</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/5_12_25_23_7thFirst/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/5_12_25_23_7thFirst/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’ve been taking practice inspiration from Mark Levine’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Jazz-Theory-Book-Mark-Levine/dp/1883217040">Jazz Theory Book</a>. This exercise wasn’t in there specifically, but it’s in the spirit of root-bias deprogramming.</p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/5_12_25_23_7thFirst/levine.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>Levine has these fun quips throughout that I’m trying to follow through on:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Remember, practice all scales and patterns both ascending and descending; on the major, melodic minor, diminished, and whole-tone scales and in all keys</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>You’ve now learned about all four of the scales you’ll need under your fingers to play over chord changes. The next question is how to practice them. And you don’t just want to practice them, but to internalize them to the point where they become an <strong>available pool of notes</strong>, on which to improvise.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>…the goal is to deprogram yourself from years of root-bias conditioning</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I learned piano in the classical music tradition and practiced all my scales and chords in a massively root-biased way when I was a kid. So, one of my goals right now is to think about chords from non-root perspectives.</p>
<p>For example, in this exercise my goal is to practice leading with the 7th note. This is related to the exercise from yesterday, but I did few things differently. Here’s the idea:</p>
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/5_12_25_23_7thFirst/7thfirst-01.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Play II-V-I chords through the circle of fifths</li>
<li>For each chord, lead with the 7th note, then bounce between the 7th note and each inversion of the 7th chord.</li>
</ol>
<p>In the first bar I have a D-7 chord in the key of C major. The minor 7th note is a C, and instead of thinking C = C major, I’m trying to also think C = D-7 . And, by doing this around the circle of fifths, you end up practicing every kind of 7th chord (maj, dom, min) for every key.</p>
<p>This exercise implies some related ones that I’ll get to some other day, such as leading with the 5th, or leading with the 3rd…and then leading with the weirder stuff (sus, b5, b9, #11).</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/5_12_25_23_7thFirst/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/5_12_25_23_7thFirst/levine.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="186" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scales in 7th chords</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/4_12_24_23_scales_7ths/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/4_12_24_23_scales_7ths/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“An armadillo piano player practicing playing piano in the middle of a desert with a bright blue sky” - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p><audio controls=""> <source src="scake_maj7ths.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<p>This exercise has two parts. Practice around the circle of fifths.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Play the major scale up and down using 7th chords.</li>
</ol>
<p>I<sup>∆7</sup> II<sup>-7</sup> III<sup>-7</sup> IV<sup>∆7</sup> V<sup>7</sup> VI<sup>-7</sup> VII<sup>-Dim7</sup></p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Play each chord as an arpeggio, but start on the 7th and play down to the root.</li>
</ol>
<p>Notes: very easy to burn through this in C without thinking. G and F are decent, everything else is slow. Need to keep practicing the hard ones.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/4_12_24_23_scales_7ths/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/4_12_24_23_scales_7ths/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cycling through Major 7ths</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/3_12_23_23_cycling/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><audio controls=""> <source src="Maj7ths_01.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<p>The basic task is to play Major 7th chords through the circle of fifths.</p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>Circle of fifths</p>
<p>Going clockwise the next note is a perfect fifth from the previous note.</p>
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/3_12_23_23_cycling/circle.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>Major 7th chords have a I-III-V-maj7 structure. These are the first, third, fifth, and major 7th notes in the major scale of the root key. For example, the key of C has 7 notes in the major scale: C D E F G A B</p>
<p>The chord C Maj7 (also notated as C∆7) is C-E-G-B.</p>
<p>Where C is the root or first note, E is the III, G is the V, and B is the major VII. The same pattern is applied to make Maj7 chords in all other keys.</p>
<p>At the beginning of this practice track I play chords going anti-clockwise through the circle of fifths:</p>
<p>C∆7 - F∆7 - Bb∆7 - Eb∆7 - Ab∆7 - Db∆7 - Gb∆7 - B∆7 - E∆7 - A∆7 - D∆7 - G∆7 - C∆7</p>
<p>I can probably play through this a bit faster, but not without making mistakes. One goal is to get the speed up both in both directions (anti-clockwise and clockwise).</p>
<p>Next, there is a short riff that I got from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CML0EgoqpxU">Nahre Sol’s youtube channel</a>, who has some other great recommendations for playing through maj7th chords.</p>
<p>Then, I end with playing ∆7th chords in my left hand and messing around with playing through major scales in the right hand. For example, if I’m playing a C∆7th, then I’m playing through the C major scale and so on. I thought I would have a better grasp on all of the major scales, but some of them are way out of practice. Yeesh. Baby steps.</p>
<p>A random observation about musical relationships that this exercise drew out. When playing anti-clockwise, the next chord remains ambiguous with respect to the tonal center: it could indicate a switch of the root, but maybe not. There isn’t enough evidence to go on based on the notes in the major 7th chords.</p>
<p>For example, going from C∆7 to F∆7 involves CEGB and FACE, all of these notes are in the C Major scale. So, the F∆7 chord doesn’t add any new notes, which in my mind allows some ambiguity about whether we are in C major still or have switched to F major. The F major scale has a Bb, which is the one note that makes F major different from C major, but this note is not voiced in the F∆7 chord. However, this “new note”, which would provide evidence that the root had switched from C to F is voiced by the next chord in the circle of fifths, Bb. So, in some sense moving anti-clockwise by one chord sets up a question—has the root changed?—and moving one more chord answers the question—yes—, but also asks the same question again, in a circle of fifths.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice exercise</category>
  <category>circle of fifths</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/3_12_23_23_cycling/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/3_12_23_23_cycling/circle.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="135" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Practice</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/2_12_23_23_practice/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/2_12_23_23_practice/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“A piano keyboard shaped like a perfect circle. Very bright and colorful. Lightning bolts in the sky.” - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p>Back into practicing the piano and working on my chops. It’s been a little bit painful because I am so out of practice. Perhaps there is a new year’s resolution here to practice more. But, what to practice?</p>
<p>My recent routine is working through the circle of fifths and reclaiming some basics.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Playing Maj7 chords anti-clockwise and then clockwise through the circle of fifths</li>
<li>Playing II-V-I through the circle of fifths</li>
<li>Playing V7-V7 through the circle of fifths</li>
<li>Playing I-VI-II-V through the circle of fifths. This is the same progression as in “Heart and Soul”, a duet we’d play as kids. Currently, I’m asking the question whether I can play this song effortlessly (chords in the left hand, melody in the right) in a key as I go around the circle, and if the answer is yes, I shouldn’t practice this key, and if the answer is no, then I should.</li>
</ol>
<p>Starting to get some fluency back. I was never that diligent at practicing through all of the keys, and some of them need a lot of work.</p>
<p>Ideally, I’d like to keep a little journal here of practice strategies, reporting on: what I’m doing, what I’m hoping to get out of it (or did get out of it), and other observations that could relate to musical connections and/or connections to the cognitive science of skill learning.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>motivation</category>
  <category>circle of fifths</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/2_12_23_23_practice/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/2_12_23_23_practice/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Dolphin Dance</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/1_12_20_23_dolphin_dance/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/1_12_20_23_dolphin_dance/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>” Herbie Hancock’s dolphin dance with a bunch of synthesizers” - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p><audio controls=""> <source src="DolphinDanceFull_render 2_01.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<p>Have been messing about with Herbie Hancock’s “Dolphin Dance” on the piano for a while.</p>
<p>Had a clear day to try some mixer mimicking. Plan was to develop my own voicings for everything, but mix them similar to the Maiden Voyage recording…and then jam it.</p>
<p>What happened:</p>
<ul>
<li>Recorded the Hancock version into Ableton</li>
<li>Located BPM</li>
<li>Voices
<ul>
<li>Rhodes</li>
<li>Moog matriarch bass lines</li>
<li>MPC drums</li>
<li>OB-6 horns</li>
</ul></li>
<li>For each voice, play with the original record. Keep recording in a loop using Ableton comping lanes</li>
<li>Fix messes by sampling in comping lanes/ explore have fun with fixing the mess</li>
<li>Duplicate the head, then solo overtop for a bit</li>
<li>Mix it down.</li>
<li>Try some final mixing touches.</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>quarto</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/1_12_20_23_dolphin_dance/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/1_12_20_23_dolphin_dance/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>blog template</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/template/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/template/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“fragments of a dream woven together with little puzzle pieces showing a universe of possibility” - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p><audio controls=""> <source src="file.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<p>Nothing to see here. This is the template file I use to start posts.</p>
<p>Post goes here.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/template/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/template/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
