<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Homophony</title>
<link>https://homophony.quest/notes.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://homophony.quest/notes.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Music blog for motivation to play more music</description>
<image>
<url>https://homophony.quest/images/notesE_0.jpg</url>
<title>Homophony</title>
<link>https://homophony.quest/notes.html</link>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.4.533</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Blogging for music motivation</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/1_12_27_23_blog/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I had some time at the end of my semester to play piano more than usual. This semester that meant I actually played the piano, instead of not playing the piano.</p>
<p>Clearly I need to make time for more piano. I’m hoping this blog will keep me somewhat organized and motivated to stay on target.</p>
<p>The blog is built with <a href="https://quarto.org">quarto</a>, and this post is just changing the structure a little bit so that each post is it’s own post, rather than a bunch of posts on a single page.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>quarto</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/1_12_27_23_blog/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/1_12_27_23_blog/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Freddie Freeloader Wynton Kelly solo</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/7_12_27_23_freddie/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/7_12_27_23_freddie/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“A small penguin wearing headphones. The penguin listens to the music from the headphones. The penguin sits in front of a piano. The penguin can imagine the musical notes in a tornado above her head.” - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p>I spent most of yesterday working through Wynton Kelly’s solo on Freddie Freeloader (from Miles Davis’s Kind of Blue). My plan for this post is to talk a little bit about what I did, and what I learned.</p>
<p>A slight detour though. It’s been very nice to have some clear time to actually practice piano, let alone enough time to break down a solo. When I was a kid the advice was to listen to recordings and learn to play from them by ear. In some cases I was able to do this (with difficulty, because I didn’t spend enough time practicing this way), but for the most part I didn’t have the recordings to listen to. Flash-forward to today and almost everything is available to stream. That’s amazing when you’re trying to learn something by ear. Not only that, but the internet is full of musicians sharing their practice tips. It’s almost overwhelming, but in a good way.</p>
<p>For Freddie Freeloader I checked out a couple of YouTube videos before trying the solo myself: a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XSjWOTbL5ew">transcription video</a> and an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZxfawXcpuaQ">analysis video</a>. Then I played the song a couple times before heading downstairs. Here’s the breakdown process I used this time.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Play the original recording into a track on Ableton live</li>
<li>Cut the track so that it starts properly on the first bar</li>
<li>Turn off “warp”, and then adjust the tempo of Ableton until the beats in the track line up properly with the bars in Ableton.</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/7_12_27_23_freddie/Screenshot 2023-12-27 at 7.56.08 AM.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The purple track is the original recording. The selected area is the first two bars, and it is possible to loop the selection and/or slow it down without changing the pitch (by turning warp back on).</p>
<p>I wasn’t particularly interested in learning the solo to play it note for note straight through. But, I was interested in trying out each little part and thinking about how the notes were used as phrases.</p>
<p>So, I worked in sections of two bars, looped each section, then played over top on the Fender Rhodes until I thought I had the line. The blue track are my 2 bar recordings on the Rhodes.</p>
<p>I didn’t have time to get through the whole solo, just the first 12 bars, and it got a little messy at the end. Oh well. Had lots of fun.</p>
<p><audio controls=""> <source src="Freddie_solo.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<p>Practice notes: I ended up practicing the first phrase through the circle of fifths this morning.</p>
<p><audio controls=""> <source src="freddie_phrase.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/7_12_27_23_freddie/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/7_12_27_23_freddie/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rootless 9th chords</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/6_12_26_23_rootless9th/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/6_12_26_23_rootless9th/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“An underground lair of piano playing rabbits. Above the rabbits are the roots of carrots that have been eaten by rabbits as they play piano.” - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p>Today’s exercise was running I∆7add9 chords through the circle of fifths.</p>
<p>The first row shows the notes of the C major scale with corresponding numbers. The 9th note is the same as the second note in the scale.</p>
<p>The second row shows the concept of constructing chords from thirds. From this perspective, you get all of the notes in the scale going up by thirds, but the 9th, 11th, and 13th note are out of their normal order.</p>
<p>This exercise focuses on the “rootless” 9th chord on the bottom row. That one has a major 3rd, a perfect fifth, a major 7th, and a 9th.</p>
<table class="table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 6%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>1</th>
<th>2</th>
<th>3</th>
<th>4</th>
<th>5</th>
<th>6</th>
<th>7</th>
<th>8</th>
<th>9</th>
<th>10</th>
<th>11</th>
<th>12</th>
<th>13</th>
<th>14</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>C</strong></td>
<td>D</td>
<td><strong>E</strong></td>
<td>F</td>
<td><strong>G</strong></td>
<td>A</td>
<td><strong>B</strong></td>
<td>C</td>
<td><strong>D</strong></td>
<td>E</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>G</td>
<td>A</td>
<td>B</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>C</td>
<td></td>
<td>E</td>
<td></td>
<td>G</td>
<td></td>
<td>B</td>
<td></td>
<td>D</td>
<td></td>
<td>F</td>
<td></td>
<td>A</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>E</td>
<td></td>
<td>G</td>
<td></td>
<td>B</td>
<td></td>
<td>D</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>In the exercise I played these chords clockwise and anti-clockwise through the circle of fifths. I usually used my left hand for the bass note and to remind myself where I was in the circle. Then I played versions of the 9th chord. They all have a smashing pumpkins kind of vibe.</p>
<p>One reason I chose this exercise is to press harder on deprogramming my root conditioning. These chords don’t have the root in them, so they must be good for that (e.g., thinking about doing something in C, but not playing C, or only playing around C).</p>
<p>Another musical connection is that these 9th chords are the same as a III-7 chord. So, an E minor 7th is a C major 7th add 9.</p>
<p>Cognitive science connections: As a sidenote, my day job is a cognitive psychology professor who studies skill-learning. I’ve been meaning to do some piano skill research and I even have the keyboards in my lab to do it. So, as I go through these exercises it’s been fun thinking about issues like how does training on some musical ideas transfer to others.</p>
<p>For example, I’m already fairly fluid at playing the circle of fifths in different ways. If I’m playing single notes, I can go through the circle very quickly. It’s slower for chords, but still fairly quick. I’ve been practicing my 7th chords through the circle, so I can already go through the circle playing minor 7th chords fairly quickly. However, it turns out I can not do these 9th chords quickly. There should be pretty good transfer here because the 9th chords are exactly the same as the minor 7th chords that I have already practiced.</p>
<p>In terms of minor 7th chords I had been practicing these chords, with the root in the bass.</p>
<table class="table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>1</th>
<th>2</th>
<th>3</th>
<th>4</th>
<th>5</th>
<th>6</th>
<th>7</th>
<th>8</th>
<th>9</th>
<th>10</th>
<th>11</th>
<th>12</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>E-7</td>
<td>B-7</td>
<td>Gb-7</td>
<td>Db-7</td>
<td>Ab-7</td>
<td>Eb-7</td>
<td>Bb-7</td>
<td>F-7</td>
<td>C-7</td>
<td>G-7</td>
<td>D-7</td>
<td>A-7</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>E</td>
<td>B</td>
<td>Gb</td>
<td>Db</td>
<td>Ab</td>
<td>Eb</td>
<td>Bb</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>C</td>
<td>G</td>
<td>D</td>
<td>A</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>But, I had not been practicing those chords with the following bass notes.</p>
<table class="table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>1</th>
<th>2</th>
<th>3</th>
<th>4</th>
<th>5</th>
<th>6</th>
<th>7</th>
<th>8</th>
<th>9</th>
<th>10</th>
<th>11</th>
<th>12</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>E-7</td>
<td>B-7</td>
<td>Gb-7</td>
<td>Db-7</td>
<td>Ab-7</td>
<td>Eb-7</td>
<td>Bb-7</td>
<td>F-7</td>
<td>C-7</td>
<td>G-7</td>
<td>D-7</td>
<td>A-7</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>C</td>
<td>G</td>
<td>D</td>
<td>A</td>
<td>E</td>
<td>B</td>
<td>Gb</td>
<td>Db</td>
<td>Ab</td>
<td>Eb</td>
<td>Bb</td>
<td>F</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Generalization is so fickle sometimes.</p>
<p>Also, I have some super-biased thirds. What’s the third of C -&gt; E. No problem, that’s fast. A -&gt; C, G -&gt; B. But, B ———&gt; Eb. That one hurts. Eb seems too far away to be a third. In any case. I need to flatten out this distribution at some point.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/6_12_26_23_rootless9th/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/6_12_26_23_rootless9th/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>7th first II-V-I</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/5_12_25_23_7thFirst/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/5_12_25_23_7thFirst/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’ve been taking practice inspiration from Mark Levine’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Jazz-Theory-Book-Mark-Levine/dp/1883217040">Jazz Theory Book</a>. This exercise wasn’t in there specifically, but it’s in the spirit of root-bias deprogramming.</p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/5_12_25_23_7thFirst/levine.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>Levine has these fun quips throughout that I’m trying to follow through on:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Remember, practice all scales and patterns both ascending and descending; on the major, melodic minor, diminished, and whole-tone scales and in all keys</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>You’ve now learned about all four of the scales you’ll need under your fingers to play over chord changes. The next question is how to practice them. And you don’t just want to practice them, but to internalize them to the point where they become an <strong>available pool of notes</strong>, on which to improvise.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>…the goal is to deprogram yourself from years of root-bias conditioning</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I learned piano in the classical music tradition and practiced all my scales and chords in a massively root-biased way when I was a kid. So, one of my goals right now is to think about chords from non-root perspectives.</p>
<p>For example, in this exercise my goal is to practice leading with the 7th note. This is related to the exercise from yesterday, but I did few things differently. Here’s the idea:</p>
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/5_12_25_23_7thFirst/7thfirst-01.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Play II-V-I chords through the circle of fifths</li>
<li>For each chord, lead with the 7th note, then bounce between the 7th note and each inversion of the 7th chord.</li>
</ol>
<p>In the first bar I have a D-7 chord in the key of C major. The minor 7th note is a C, and instead of thinking C = C major, I’m trying to also think C = D-7 . And, by doing this around the circle of fifths, you end up practicing every kind of 7th chord (maj, dom, min) for every key.</p>
<p>This exercise implies some related ones that I’ll get to some other day, such as leading with the 5th, or leading with the 3rd…and then leading with the weirder stuff (sus, b5, b9, #11).</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/5_12_25_23_7thFirst/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/5_12_25_23_7thFirst/levine.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="186" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scales in 7th chords</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/4_12_24_23_scales_7ths/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/4_12_24_23_scales_7ths/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“An armadillo piano player practicing playing piano in the middle of a desert with a bright blue sky” - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p><audio controls=""> <source src="scake_maj7ths.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<p>This exercise has two parts. Practice around the circle of fifths.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Play the major scale up and down using 7th chords.</li>
</ol>
<p>I<sup>∆7</sup> II<sup>-7</sup> III<sup>-7</sup> IV<sup>∆7</sup> V<sup>7</sup> VI<sup>-7</sup> VII<sup>-Dim7</sup></p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Play each chord as an arpeggio, but start on the 7th and play down to the root.</li>
</ol>
<p>Notes: very easy to burn through this in C without thinking. G and F are decent, everything else is slow. Need to keep practicing the hard ones.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/4_12_24_23_scales_7ths/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/4_12_24_23_scales_7ths/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cycling through Major 7ths</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/3_12_23_23_cycling/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><audio controls=""> <source src="Maj7ths_01.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<p>The basic task is to play Major 7th chords through the circle of fifths.</p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>Circle of fifths</p>
<p>Going clockwise the next note is a perfect fifth from the previous note.</p>
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/3_12_23_23_cycling/circle.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>Major 7th chords have a I-III-V-maj7 structure. These are the first, third, fifth, and major 7th notes in the major scale of the root key. For example, the key of C has 7 notes in the major scale: C D E F G A B</p>
<p>The chord C Maj7 (also notated as C∆7) is C-E-G-B.</p>
<p>Where C is the root or first note, E is the III, G is the V, and B is the major VII. The same pattern is applied to make Maj7 chords in all other keys.</p>
<p>At the beginning of this practice track I play chords going anti-clockwise through the circle of fifths:</p>
<p>C∆7 - F∆7 - Bb∆7 - Eb∆7 - Ab∆7 - Db∆7 - Gb∆7 - B∆7 - E∆7 - A∆7 - D∆7 - G∆7 - C∆7</p>
<p>I can probably play through this a bit faster, but not without making mistakes. One goal is to get the speed up both in both directions (anti-clockwise and clockwise).</p>
<p>Next, there is a short riff that I got from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CML0EgoqpxU">Nahre Sol’s youtube channel</a>, who has some other great recommendations for playing through maj7th chords.</p>
<p>Then, I end with playing ∆7th chords in my left hand and messing around with playing through major scales in the right hand. For example, if I’m playing a C∆7th, then I’m playing through the C major scale and so on. I thought I would have a better grasp on all of the major scales, but some of them are way out of practice. Yeesh. Baby steps.</p>
<p>A random observation about musical relationships that this exercise drew out. When playing anti-clockwise, the next chord remains ambiguous with respect to the tonal center: it could indicate a switch of the root, but maybe not. There isn’t enough evidence to go on based on the notes in the major 7th chords.</p>
<p>For example, going from C∆7 to F∆7 involves CEGB and FACE, all of these notes are in the C Major scale. So, the F∆7 chord doesn’t add any new notes, which in my mind allows some ambiguity about whether we are in C major still or have switched to F major. The F major scale has a Bb, which is the one note that makes F major different from C major, but this note is not voiced in the F∆7 chord. However, this “new note”, which would provide evidence that the root had switched from C to F is voiced by the next chord in the circle of fifths, Bb. So, in some sense moving anti-clockwise by one chord sets up a question—has the root changed?—and moving one more chord answers the question—yes—, but also asks the same question again, in a circle of fifths.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice exercise</category>
  <category>circle of fifths</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/3_12_23_23_cycling/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/3_12_23_23_cycling/circle.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="135" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Practice</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/2_12_23_23_practice/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/2_12_23_23_practice/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“A piano keyboard shaped like a perfect circle. Very bright and colorful. Lightning bolts in the sky.” - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p>Back into practicing the piano and working on my chops. It’s been a little bit painful because I am so out of practice. Perhaps there is a new year’s resolution here to practice more. But, what to practice?</p>
<p>My recent routine is working through the circle of fifths and reclaiming some basics.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Playing Maj7 chords anti-clockwise and then clockwise through the circle of fifths</li>
<li>Playing II-V-I through the circle of fifths</li>
<li>Playing V7-V7 through the circle of fifths</li>
<li>Playing I-VI-II-V through the circle of fifths. This is the same progression as in “Heart and Soul”, a duet we’d play as kids. Currently, I’m asking the question whether I can play this song effortlessly (chords in the left hand, melody in the right) in a key as I go around the circle, and if the answer is yes, I shouldn’t practice this key, and if the answer is no, then I should.</li>
</ol>
<p>Starting to get some fluency back. I was never that diligent at practicing through all of the keys, and some of them need a lot of work.</p>
<p>Ideally, I’d like to keep a little journal here of practice strategies, reporting on: what I’m doing, what I’m hoping to get out of it (or did get out of it), and other observations that could relate to musical connections and/or connections to the cognitive science of skill learning.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>motivation</category>
  <category>circle of fifths</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/2_12_23_23_practice/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/2_12_23_23_practice/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Dolphin Dance</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/1_12_20_23_dolphin_dance/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/1_12_20_23_dolphin_dance/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>” Herbie Hancock’s dolphin dance with a bunch of synthesizers” - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p><audio controls=""> <source src="DolphinDanceFull_render 2_01.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<p>Have been messing about with Herbie Hancock’s “Dolphin Dance” on the piano for a while.</p>
<p>Had a clear day to try some mixer mimicking. Plan was to develop my own voicings for everything, but mix them similar to the Maiden Voyage recording…and then jam it.</p>
<p>What happened:</p>
<ul>
<li>Recorded the Hancock version into Ableton</li>
<li>Located BPM</li>
<li>Voices
<ul>
<li>Rhodes</li>
<li>Moog matriarch bass lines</li>
<li>MPC drums</li>
<li>OB-6 horns</li>
</ul></li>
<li>For each voice, play with the original record. Keep recording in a loop using Ableton comping lanes</li>
<li>Fix messes by sampling in comping lanes/ explore have fun with fixing the mess</li>
<li>Duplicate the head, then solo overtop for a bit</li>
<li>Mix it down.</li>
<li>Try some final mixing touches.</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>quarto</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/1_12_20_23_dolphin_dance/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/1_12_20_23_dolphin_dance/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>blog template</title>
  <dc:creator>Matt Crump</dc:creator>
  <link>https://homophony.quest/blog/template/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://homophony.quest/blog/template/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>“fragments of a dream woven together with little puzzle pieces showing a universe of possibility” - LCM_Dreamshaper_v7</p>
</div></div><p><audio controls=""> <source src="file.mp3" type="audio/wav"> </audio></p>
<p>Nothing to see here. This is the template file I use to start posts.</p>
<p>Post goes here.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://homophony.quest/blog/template/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://homophony.quest/blog/template/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
